To check for Python 39, you'll want to pull up a terminal.
So if I run Python 3, dash dash version, I should see Python 39.
You should see that as well.
It's especially important to install the latest version of Python because your machine,
especially if you're running a Mac, might already come with a version of Python, depending
on your OS.
It might be an older one, so we want to make sure that we're working with the latest
and greatest.
Now, we want to make a project directory and create a virtual environment in it.
So for this example, let me start off from the same point that you're all starting off
at, make a directory, make sure that you're in your home directory.
So in this case for Macro Linux, just CD to home and then make a directory called
Pi Workshop and CD into it should be an empty directory.
Now, we want to create a virtual environment and activate it.
In order to do that, we're going to use Python 3, dash, the dash m means run this next
command as a module, which is going to be the Python 3 built in virtual environments.
And the next command is going to be a name.
In this case, I'm just going to call it the standard n.
It's a pretty good idea to name your virtual environments and because if you're using a standard
get ignore for Python, this is one of the folders that's going to be automatically excluded.
And you're not going to want these auto generated files to end up in your get repository.
Now, if I take a look here, I should see a ENV directory.
I'm going to, I'm not going to talk about what's in this directory for the moment.
We're going to talk about that a little bit later on in the class.
But basically, it contains a standalone Python version, a standalone Python interpreter.
And when we work in that interpreter, we are guaranteed that we are using the version of Python
that we used when we created it.
And any packages that we install when that virtual environment is activated are going to stay in
that virtual environment and not pollute your system settings.
So working in a virtual environment for a project no matter how small it is is generally a pretty good
idea. In order to activate it on Mac, I'm going to source n slash bin slash activate.
And your terminal might not be as fancy as mine. You'll probably see something that looks like this.
It'll say end in parentheses followed by the rest of your prompt.
And that means that the virtual environment is now activated.
Now I can type Python in here. I don't need the three anymore. And the Python executable points
to that version of Python that we used when we created the virtual environment.
You also want to make sure that you have VS code. If you are running on Mac and you recently
installed VS code, you might not have the code executable. You can check if you have it by typing
code dash dash version. If you are on a Mac and you don't see anything here, you might have to follow
an extra step. Sorry, that is right here, which is called launching from the command line
install code command on path. I'll show you how to bring up this dialog box in a second.
But if you're not seeing it, the instructions are right there.
Now we want to do a little bit of configuration for VS code. We want to make sure that we have the
Python extension installed. You're not going to see anything from the Python extension until you
open your very first Python file. I have a link here to some list of keymap extensions.
If you want to remap your key bindings in VS code to e-max or vim or sublime or something else.
But while we're working through the class, there's only two keyboard shortcuts that you're
going to need to remember in VS code for a Windows that is Control Shift P. And Command Shift P
on Mac for show command palette. This is like your Swiss army knife. It's going to bring up a window
where you can type and see all of the list of different commands that VS code offers. So if I bring
that up in here, if I type Python, we'll see that all of these commands are available because I've
opened a Python file and I have the Python extension activated. The other command that you need to
know is Control P on Windows or Command P on Mac. That's going to bring up the Fest File finder.
So you can type in any file name that's contained in your project and it will quickly bring it up.
If you know these two keyboard shortcuts, just write them down on a post-it note somewhere near
your desk. You're going to be using them a lot and that's really kind of all that you need to know
to get productive and Python in VS code. Now when you work with files, when you bring up a new
Python file, if you have not done that before, if you don't have a VS code installation, you might see
some various pop-ups. So let's go ahead and create a new file. It's just file new file or command
and Control N. And we're going to save this file as, oh my VS code is now angry that I have renamed
my directory. We're going to call this high.py. And if you're opening up this file for the first time,
you might see some pop-ups here asking you whether you want to install a linter, in which case you do
click yes on that. And if there are any other pop-ups for things that are missing or not installed,
go ahead and click yes and install them. There's also an optional extension that you might want to
install called Pylands. And it is an additional feature-rich language server for VS code. You don't
need to have it, but I find it pretty useful. So you want to go ahead and install that.
Make sure that when you have this Python file opened, that the correct interpreter is opened as well.
In this case, mine is the last one. So it looks like VS code didn't automatically pick it up.
Maybe because of my directory weirdness. So make sure that you go ahead and select the right
interpreter. Here you'll see that mine is in dot n slash bin slash Python. And now I'll see here
at the bottom that I have the correct version of Python. I'm just going to bump that up a little bit.
Now, what do we need to do to run Python code in VS code? We've already gone ahead and created
in you file. Let's copy this into our new file and run it. There are a few different options for
running your Python files. I'll show you how to run them both from within VS code and from the terminal.
So I pasted that right in there. If you're already in VS code, you can open up the command
palette with command shift p or control shift p and select Python run Python file and terminal.
And this has the advantage of VS code being smart. And if your virtual environment is an
activated it will automatically select it. And we'll see that it output right in the included terminal
window right here at the bottom. You can also navigate to this file in your terminal and make
sure that your virtual environment is activated and run Python. Hi.py. So this is outside of VS code
if you're more comfortable in a separate terminal or on the command line.